<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-idr-link-bandwidth-09"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP Link Bandwidth Extended Community">BGP Link Bandwidth
    Extended Community</title>

    <author fullname="Pradosh Mohapatra" initials="P." surname="Mohapatra">
      <organization>Sproute Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <email>pradosh@sproute.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rex Fernando" initials="R." surname="Fernando">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rex@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Reshma Das" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Das">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dreshma@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Satya Mohanty" initials="S." role="editor"
            surname="Mohanty">
      <organization>Zscaler</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>120 Holger Way,</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>smohanty@zscaler.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mankamana Mishra" initials="M." surname="Mishra">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>821 alder drive,</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95035</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mankamis@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="03" month="09" year="2024"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes an application of BGP extended communities
      that allows a router to perform unequal cost load balancing.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Load balancing is a critical aspect of network design, enabling
      efficient utilization of available bandwidth and improving overall
      network performance. Traditional equal-cost multi-path (ECMP) routing
      does not account for the varying capacities of different paths. This
      document suggests that the external link bandwidth be carried in the
      network using one of two new extended communities <xref target="RFC4360"/>
      - the transitive and non-transitive link bandwidth extended community. 
      The Link Bandwidth Extended Community
      provides a mechanism for routers to advertise the bandwidth of their
      downstream path(s), facilitating maximum utilisation of network resources.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Link Bandwidth Extended Community">
      <t>The Link Bandwidth Extended Communities are defined as a BGP extended
      community that carries the bandwidth information of a router, represented by
      BGP Protocol Next Hop, connecting to remote network. 
      This community can be used to inform other routers about the
      available bandwidth on trough a given route.</t>

      <t>Two extended communities are both optional, one transitive and other
      non-transitive. Therefore the value of the high-order octet of the extended
      Type Field is 0x00 or 0x40 respectivly. 
      The value of the low-order octet of the extended type field for
      this communities is 0x04. The value of the Global Administrator subfield
      in the Value Field SHOULD represent the Autonomous System of the router
      that attaches the Link Bandwidth Community, but in can be set to any 4B value.
      If four octet AS numbering scheme is used <xref target="RFC6793"/>, AS_TRANS
      should be used in the Global Administrator subfield.
      The bandwidth of the link is expressed as <xfef target="IEEE754-2019"/> binary32
      interchenge floating point format, units being bytes (not bits!)
      per second. It is carried in the Local Administrator subfield of the
      Value Field.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Procedures">
      <section anchor="Originator"
               title="Sender (Originating Link Bandwidth Community)">
        <t>An originator of the link bandwidth community SHOULD be able to
        originate either a transitive or a non-transitive link bandwidth
        extended community. Implementation SHOULD provide configuration to set
        the transitivity type of the link bandwidth community, as well as Global
        Administrator filed value and bandwidth value in (Local Administrator
        filed), trough local policy.&nbsp;No more
        than one link bandwidth extended community SHALL be attached to a
        route.</t>
        <t>An originator can attach link bandwidth community to BGP path in
        egress processing to adj-RIB-out only or in ingress processing in which
        case link bandwidth community is present in Local-RIB.</t>
        <section anchor="Egress"
               title="Originating in egress processing">
          <t>When link bandwidth community is inserted in egress bgp path processing,
          it is present in adj-RIB-out only and is send to BGP peers, regardless
          of session type (interbal vs. external) and community transitivity bit.
          The link bandwidth community has no impact on sender's forwarding
          behavioiour.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Ingress"
                 title="Originating in ingress processing">
          <t>When link bandwidth community is inserted in ingress bgp path processing,
          it is present in Local-RIB, and:</t>
          <ul spacing=normal>
            <li>The transitive link bandwidth community is send to BGP peers, regardless
            of session type (interbal vs. external)</li>
            <li>The non-transitive link bandwidth community is send to internal BGP peers
            only.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>Note: Implementation may provide configuration option (knob) to allow sending
          of non-transitive link bandwidth communities to external BGP sessiosns.</t>
          <t>Since link bandwidth community is present in LOCAL-RIB, it may be used by
          sender to construct weighted ECMP forwarding behaviour (provided BGP
          multipath is in use)</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Receiver"
               title="Receiver (Receiving link bandwidth community)&nbsp;">
        <t>A BGP receiver MUST be able to process link bandwidth community of
        both transitive or non-transitive type. The receiver SHOULD NOT flap
        or treat the route as malformed based on the transitivity of the link
        bandwidth community and/or BGP session type (internal vs. external).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Re-advertisement" title="Re-advertisement Procedures">
        <section anchor="NextHopSelf"
                 title="Re-advertisement with Next hop Self">
          <t>When a BGP speaker re-advertises a route with the Link Bandwidth
          Extended Community and sets the next hop to itself, it SHOULD follow
          the same procedures as outlined in <xref target="Ingress"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="NextHopUnchanged"
                 title=" Re-advertisement with Next Hop Unchanged">
          <t>A BGP speaker that receives a route with link bandwidth
          community, re-advertises or reflects the same without changing its
          next hop SHOULD NOT change the link bandwidth extended community in
          any way.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Link bandwidth community aritmetics and BGP multipath">
      <t>In BGP multi-path ECMP enviroment, send or re-advertised link-bandwidth
      community value may be calculated based on link bandwidth communities of
      multipath-conmtributing routes in Local-RIB. This subject is out of scope 
      of this document</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Error" title="Error Handling">
      <t>If a receiver receives a route with more than one Link Bandwidth
      Extended Community, it SHOULD:<list>
          <t>Prefer the lowest value of the attached link bandwidth community
          (Irrespective of the transitivity)</t>

          <t>Prefer the transitive Link Bandwidth Extended Community when
          choosing between transitive and non-transitive types that have the
          same value</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Implementations MAY provide configuration options (knobs) to change
      the above preference.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines a specific application of the two-octet AS
      specific extended community. IANA is requested to assign a sub- type
      value of 0x04 for the link bandwidth extended community.<figure>
          <artwork>    Name                                           Value
    ----                                           -----
    non-transitive Link Bandwidth Ext. Community   0x4004</artwork>
        </figure><figure>
          <artwork>    Name                                           Value
    ----                                           -----
    transitive Link Bandwidth Ext. Community       0x0004</artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are no additional security risks introduced by this design.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors">
      <author fullname="Kaliraj Vairavakkalai" initials="K."
              surname="Vairavakkalai">
        <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

            <city>Sunnyvale</city>

            <region>CA</region>

            <code>94089</code>

            <country>US</country>
          </postal>

          <email>kaliraj@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="Natrajan Venkataraman" initials="N."
              surname="Venkataraman">
        <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

            <city>Sunnyvale</city>

            <region>CA</region>

            <code>94089</code>

            <country>US</country>
          </postal>

          <email>natv@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>

    <author fullname="Rafal Jan Szarecki" initials="R.J."
              surname="Szarecki">
        <organization>Google LLC</organization>

        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>1160 N Mathilda Ave,,</street>

            <city>Sunnyvale</city>

            <region>CA</region>

            <code>94089</code>

            <country>US</country>
          </postal>

          <email>rszarecki@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Yakov Rekhter, Srihari Sangli and Dan
      Tappan for proposing unequal cost load balancing as one possible
      application of the extended community attribute.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank Bruno Decraene, Robert Raszuk, Joel
      Halpern, Aleksi Suhonen, Randy Bush, Jeff Haas and John Scudder for
      their comments and contributions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6793.xml"?>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml6/reference.R.IEEE.754-2019.xml"/>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
